Preliminary Inventory to the Lee Telesco Collection, 1942-1953
Hoover Institution Archives
Lee Telesco Collection,
1942-1953
47025
Telesco, Lee
1 manuscript box 0.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Reports, letters, proclamations, newsletters, and miscellanea, relating to Allied guerrilla and intelligence activities in the Philippines during World War II, especially to activities of the First MacArthur Division. Includes examples of Japanese propaganda and reports of Japanese atrocities in the Philippines.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1947.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Propaganda, Japanese.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Atrocities.; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; World War, 1939-1945--Secret service.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; Japan.; Philippines.; Philippines--History--Japanese occupation, 1942-1945.
Container List
- Carbic, J. A., to Colonel Lee Telesco, 1953 December 4, relating to the Philippine Rural Reconstruction Movement (Box 1)
- Communications between Lt. Colonel James Cushing, Commander, 1st Cebu Co., Philippine Guerrillas, and Takeshi Watanabe, Commander, Imperial Japanese naval garrison of Cebu, over the return of a high Japanese admiral who crashed into guerrilla territory, 1944 May 17-28
- Filipino-American guerrillas. Central and southern Luzon area. Office of the chief of staff. Official reports to the Commander-in-chief, United States Armed forces in the Far East, of Miguel Pendon and Z. B. Marquez on their personal accomplishments as guerrilla chiefs, 1945
- Identification papers documenting the release of one Jesus Gregas, prisoner of war, under Japanese administration in the Philippines, 1943
- Luzon guerrilla army forces. Communiqué to General MacArthur on the operational history of the Luzon Guerrilla Army Force, 1945
- Philippine Islands (Territory under Japanese Occupation). Imperial Japanese Forces. Defense Headquarters, Manila. Announcement signed by Leon Guinto, Military Governor, 1945 January 6
- United States Army. First MacArthur Division (Guerrilla Unit). Directives documenting activities, 1945 January-February
- United States Army. First MacArthur Division (Guerrilla Unit). War news flashes, mostly concerning operations in the Philippines, compiled and distributed by the First MacArthur Division, 1944 December 1-1945 January 30
- United States Army. Forces in the Far East. Founding of the first MacArthur Commandos, its accomplishments and aims as of August 1, 1942, by Colonel J. A. Roddy, Commander. Together with letters documenting some of its activities, 1945 February-March
- United States Army. Forces in the Pacific. Guerrilla weather operations in the Philippines, 194-
- United States Army. Forces in the Pacific. Maps and charts representing activities of GHQ intelligence agents operating on Mindanao, Mindoro and Busuanga, 194-
- United States Army. Forces in the Far East. Report on atrocities committed by the Japanese against civilians and guerrillas at Cemeterio Del Norte, Philippines, 1945 May
- United States Army. Forces in the Pacific. Report of conference called by General Yamashita on December 16, 1944, at Santa Mesa, at which plans were laid for the defense of Luzon
- United States Army. 109th division. Affidavits of civilian intelligence operators declaring expenses made in connection with intelligence and sabotage work in the Philippines, 1945 June
- United States Army. Southwest Pacific area. General headquarters. Commander-in-chief (MacArthur). Message to President Truman pleading for immediate American military aid to relieve the Philippine situation, 1943 July 20
- United States Army. Southwest Pacific area. General Headquarters. Commander-in-chief (MacArthur). General MacArthur's instruction to all Filipino patriots, 1944 October 26, together with his speech delivered in honor of the Filipino patriots, 1944 November 10
- United States Army. Southwest Pacific area. General Headquarters. Commander-in-chief (MacArthur). Message to the people of the Philippines conveying to them the 1943 October 6 message of the President of the United States to Congress, which recommends post-war rehabilitation measures for the Philippines, together with message of encouragement from General MacArthur, 1943 October 16
- A collection of Japanese propaganda distributed in the Philippines during World War II
- Short wave news, guerrilla underground publication